<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article class="whitepaper">
<articleinfo>
	<title>Dispense2 manual</title>
	<author><firstname>Maks</firstname> <surname>Verver</surname></author>
</articleinfo>

<section><title>Introduction</title>
<para>Dispense2 is a set of tools which allow for quick and easy distributed computing across a wide range of platforms. One major requirement is portability, which is fulfilled by implenting the tools using the Python programming language. Another major requirement is to keep things as simple as possible, so that the amount of work required to set up a distributed computation project is minimal. To achieve this goal the tools provide sensible behaviour by default and require minimal configuration. This also means that many advanced features which are available in more complex frameworks have been omitted.</para>

<para>Dispense2 is useful for simple but time-consuming applications which need to process little input and output data for a relatively big computation and (most importantly) have no dependency between the input and output data. More formally, the computation must exploit a high degree of independent parallellism. For example, an application to filter prime numbers out of a given set of big numbers, would be suitable, since it can be determined wether a number is prime or not independently of the classification of other numbers. Unsuitable are applications which require the generation of intermediate data in order to coordinate the distributed computations; for example finding the shortest path between two points in a graph, which requires a global data structure to be maintained by the different processes, is not possible. Some dependencies can be worked around (which is discussed in a later section) but in general communication between distributed processes is not possible. If you need synchronisation or communication between distributed processes, Dispense2 is not the right tool for you.</para>

<para>The Dispense2 distribution is written and maintained by Maks Verver <email>m.verver@student.utwente.nl</email>. The most recent version of the tools can be downloaded from: <ulink url="http://hell.student.utwente.nl/dispense2/dist/">http://hell.student.utwente.nl/dispense2/dist/</ulink>.</para>


</section>

<section><title>System requirements</title>
<para>The Dispense2 system is implemented using the Python programming language, which makes it reasonably portable. It should run on any Unix or Windows system with Python 2.2.X or higher installed. Version 2.1 or lower is known not to work, due of the usage of Python features introduced in version 2.2.</para>

<para>You can get Python from <ulink url="http://www.python.org/">the Python website</ulink>; or <ulink url="http://www.activestate.com/Products/ActivePython/">the ActivePython website</ulink>.</para>
</section>

<section><title>Project preperation</title>
<para>The tools work with the notion of 'work units' and 'computation results'. Each work unit is a single line of input; multi-line input is not allowed. For each work unit, computation results are generated. Depending on the problem, this can either be a single line of output (which means that for each work unit there is exactly one result) or multiple lines of output, terminated by a blank line (which mean that each work unit can have an arbitrary number of results).</para>

<para>Writing the computing application is easy; it is a regular application which reads work units (lines of input) from the standard input and writes computation results to the standard output; either a single line of output for each output, or, when working with multiple results, any number of results terminated by a single blank line. In te latter case results can not be empty strings, ofcourse, since an empty line is used to mark the end of a set of results.</para>

<para>There is one very important requirement for the computing application: <emphasis>the standard output must be flushed after a work unit has been processed</emphasis>! This means flushing after each line for single result applications and flushing after each terminating blank line for multiple result applications. Failing to do so will block some of the tools. Note that this requirement does not seem to exist for Windows applications, but for increased portability it is better to always flush.</para>
</section>

<section><title>Tools overview</title>
<para>The toolbox is based on two simple applications: dispense and enact. On each computing client, at least one instance of the enact tool is
started. If the computing application is single-threaded (which is the easiest) I suggest running one instance of enact per available processor. The enact tool requests work units from the computation host, which runs an instance of the dispense tool. Usually, the computation host can also act as a computing client, to optimize resource utilization.</para>

<para>The dispense tool generates output while it receives results. This output can be processed with another application: collect. It processes the output of the dispense tool and can be used to do various checks on the correctness and completeness of the output as well as order the results.</para>

<para>Finally, there are two applications which provide a higher-level form of managing a computation project: host and participate. The need for these applications arose from the observation that it takes a lot of careful work to get all different computers in a project to work with the right configuration, data files, and applications for their respective platforms. The host and participate tools aim to minimalize the work involved in configuring the server and clients and eliminate errors resulting from passing incompatible options to the server and clients involved in the project. The tools work with a project configuration file written in XML and require a webserver which provides this XML file and all data files (including platform-specific applications). This means creating the configuration for the project takes a bit more time, but after that, starting the server and clients is really easy. Since a typical computation project consists of many clients which need to be configured, the advantages usually exceed the cost of setting up the project configuration.</para>

<para>The tools can be configured through the command line; run any of the tools with the -h parameter for a more detailed description of which options are available and how they work. In this manual, examples will be given of how to use the tools in typical projects.</para>
</section>

<section><title>Limitations and known bugs</title>
<para>Under Windows you should always start the scripts with the Python interpreter at the command line. ActivePython makes .py-files executable but this
functionality is broken in combination with input redirection; so, under Windows, always do "python script.py args" instead of "script.py args". This should only be relevant for the execution of the dispense and collect tools (as these are the only tools that are typically used with input redirection).</para>

<para>Under Windows, setting the 'niceness' (the relative priority) of a process is not supported. Manually change the priority of the computing application using the Task Manager if desired.</para>
</section>

<section><title>Low-level usage</title><subtitle>Using dispense and enact</subtitle>
<para>Note that the dispense and enact tools communicate over TCP/IP, for which your network must be configured. The enact tool will attempt to reconnect automatically so reliability is not strictly neccessary (although it will make things a lot easier).</para>

<para>The dispense tool outputs the computation results when they become available. Because of the way the work units are distributed, the computation results are not neccessarily output in the same order as the work units were made available. Duplicate computation results may be available in the output. It is guaranteed, however, that when the dispense tool succesfully completes, results are available for all provided work units. You can use the collect tool to filter out duplicate results and reorder the results so they correspond to the order of the work units in your input file.</para>

<section><title>Example</title>
<para>The easiest way to show how the tools work, is with a simple example. Let's take the utillity <command>bc</command>, which is a command-line calculator available on many systems, as our computing application. It reads lines containing calculations such as "(1+2)*3" and prints out the result on a single line (not for large results, by the way, but let's ignore that for now), so it follows the required protocol for single line results.</para>

<para>Let's construct an input file consisting of the work units and call it <filename>sums.txt</filename>:</para>
<programlisting>123+456
8*9*7-5*4*3
666^3
</programlisting>
<para>These are seperate calculations; one on a line.  Now, suppose we want to distribute the calculation of these 'sums' among a set of worker processes. Set up a computation host with the dispense tool:</para>
<programlisting><command>python dispense.py &lt;sums.txt &gt;results.txt</command></programlisting>
<para>The dispense tool reads in the sums and writes their results to <filename>results.txt</filename>.</para>

<para>Now, start a number of enacting processes, providing the computation host and the computing application. To start one worker process on the server, for example, use: (assuming that <command>bc</command> is in your path)</para>
<programlisting><command>python enact.py bc localhost</command></programlisting>
<para>In a real situation, you would start more than one enacting process, but this
example runs so quickly that you probably don't have the time to do so. When the
dispense tool has terminated, the results are available in <filename>results.txt</filename>.</para>

<para>To get a list of results only, instead of the output in a rich format which alsocontains the work units and some other annotations, use the collect tool; for example:</para>
<programlisting><command>python collect.py -i sums.txt &lt; results.txt</command></programlisting>
<para>Which prints out the results in the same order as the sums in the input file.</para>

<para>The collect tool has a number of useful command line options; run <command>collect -h</command>. for an overview. Although in this example the use of collect.py seems a bit superfluous, it is useful for larger computations, because it does a lot of sanity checks and performs functions such as filtering out duplicate results and verifying that redundant computations returned equivalent results.</para>
</section>
</section>

<section><title>High-level usage</title><subtitle>Using host and participate</subtitle>
<para>As stated earlier, it is important that the enact and dispense tools are used consistently on the server and the clients. If the server is started with the multiple results option, all clients should be started with this option, too. Furthermore, for enact to work, each client must have a correct version of the computing application and all of the data files it might need. It follows that it takes some time and effort to set up a client. When you are working with a lot of participating clients, getting all clients to work on the same project takes a lot of work. Even if you have everything working correctly, any time you make a change to the computing application or one of it's data files, you must redistribute these new files to all participating clients. One of the design goals for Dispense2 is that setting up a distributed project should require minimal effort. For this reason, two high-level tools, called host and participate, are provided.</para>

<para>The idea behind the high-level tools are that the description of a project and all the files it needs should be seperated from the actual computers that take the role of server and clients. At the core is a project description file in XML format, which is also the only additional file that needs to be created in order to use the high-level tools. This project description file should be made available publicly through a webserver, in addition to all files required by the projects, such as input files consisting of work units, application program files for various platforms and any data files that are required by the computing application. In practice it is probably easiest to place all files in a single directory which is made available through an HTTP or FTP server.</para>

<section><title>Example</title>
<para>Let's look at a simple example of a project description file, which builds on the example described earlier in the manual:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0"?>
<project
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation=
        "http://hell.student.utwente.nl/dispense2/project.xsd"
    
    id="calc"
    name="Example project for the calculation of arbitrary expressions"
    url="http://projects.mydomain.com/calc/project.xml"
>

    <server>
        <host>projects.mydomain.com</host>
        <port>3450</port>
        <file md5="bb54a0d4c8fdb870fb57696aadc84327" name="sums.txt"
            >http://projects.mydomain.com/projects/calc/sums.txt</file>
        <input>sums.txt</input>
        <output>results.txt</output>
    </server>
	
    <client>
        <platform>win32</platform>
        <command>bc.exe</command>
    </client>
	
    <client>
        <platform>linux2</platform>
        <platform>freebsd4</platform>
        <platform>freebsd5</platform>
        <command>/usr/bin/bc</command>
    </client>

</project>
]]></programlisting>

<para>At the root of the document hierarchy is a project element. It has attributes which define a unique id for the project, as well as a more elaborate project name and the URL at which the project description file will be made available. It contains a single required server element and several (in this case: two) client elements. The server element describes the server configuration; it consists of the host and port on which the host application will bind and to which the client applications will connect. The names of the file used for input (consisting of work units) and output (consisting of the output which will be generated by the dispense tool) are also specified. The input file, ofcourse, must be filled beforehand, because it will contain the work units for the project and this is what the file element is for: it states that the server depends on a file with the local name <filename>sums.txt</filename> which is available from the URL <filename>http://projects.mydomain.com/calc/sums.txt</filename>. In addition, the MD5 hash code for the file is required as an attribute, so the integrity of the file can be verified.</para>

<para>Hosting this project is very easy. One would simply log in to the host which is specificied under the server element, and use the host tool with the URL of the project description file as an argument:</para>
<programlisting><command>python host.py http://projects.mydomain.com/calc/project.xml</command></programlisting>
<para>What happens now, is that the input file (<filename>sums.txt</filename>) is downloaded automatically, its MD5 hash code is calculated and then the dispense tool is started which binds on the host and port specified in the project description file.</para>

<para>As you can see, there are multiple client elements in the project description file. Each client element applies to a set of platforms. The platform identifiers are used as they are assigned by Python. To find out what the platform identifier for your current platform is, execute the following command:</para>
<programlisting><command>python -c "import sys; print sys.platform"</command></programlisting>
<para>The command element specifies the command as it is passed to the enact tool. As you can see, different client elements are used when different command are needed. However, different client elements are also used when the files that are needed are different. In this example we have assumed that there is a Windows version of bc available called <filename>bc.exe</filename> but this probably not the case (it is not part of the standard distribution). We should make this file available on the web server and add it to the project description as a required file for clients on the Windows platform. We would be required to change the client element so it looks something like this:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
    <client>
        <platform>win32</platform>
        <file md5="b7cb1a9378f6a210653c6ad8ec291713" name="bc.exe"
            >http://projects.mydomain.com/calc/bc.exe</file>
        <command>bc.exe</command>
    </client>
]]></programlisting>
<para>Our project is ready to run on Linux (2.x), FreeBSD (4.x and 5.x) and Windows (all versions). Clients can now be started with the following command:</para>
<programlisting><command>python participate.py http://projects.mydomain.com/calc/project.xml</command></programlisting>
<para>Note the similarity to the host command above and note that no additional options are neccessary. Clients will automatically connect to the host and port specified in the project description file, but under Windows the required computing application <filename>bc.exe</filename> will be downloaded and verified first.</para>
<para>It is important to note that under UNIX-like operating systems files can only be executed as commands if they have the executable bit of the file mode set. The mode attribute of the file element can be used to override the default file mode (determined by the active umask) of local files; for an executable file this attribute would have the value 0755.</para>
<para>An XML Schema definition is provided in the file <filename>project.xsd</filename> which formally describes the structure of the project description files. You can use the definition to validate your project description files, but it also contains a detailed description of the file format along with useful comments.</para>
</section>
</section>

<section><title>Advanced topics</title>
<section><title>Semi-dependend data</title>
<para>Unless configured otherwise, the enact tool will keep trying to reconnect to the computation host in order to receive more work. This means that you can leave the enacting processes running and independently restart the dispending process, when you have new work that needs processing (with the same computing application, of course). This can also be used to process data which depends on the results of earlier computations: create a controller application that executes a loop consisting of the execution of a dispensing process followed by the construction of a new set of work based on the partial results obtained. For example, for the computation of an opening book for a chess program, a work unit is a chess configuration (represented by a sequence of initial moves, for example). The computation consists of evaluating this configuration and the resulting value is used by the controlling application to generate new configurations based on the best configurations generated in the previous pass.</para>
</section>

<section><title>Limitations of the collect tool</title>
<para>Since the collect tool does a lot of in-memory processing, especially when provided with an original input file, it works best for small data files. If you need to process a lot data, consider splitting up the work into smaller sets of work, or do not use the ordering functionality which is activate when an original input file is provided.</para>
</section>

<section><title>Result verification and redundant computation</title>
<para>Under normal operation, the Dispense2 tools assume that although network connections may be unreliable, all clients are reliable in the sense that if they return results, these results are the correct solution to the computation problem. This means that you must have control over the computing clients and you must make sure that the computing application for all platforms is correct. While clients that crash aren't a problem (more the crash itself), clients that report incorrect results because they have incorrect applications or corrupted data files are. There are several ways of making sure that the computation results are correct.</para>
<para>Some computations have the nice property that although solving the problem is hard, verifying the solution is easy. In such cases, one could write a simple program that reads through all the results and verifies them. In many cases, this only partially true; for example, when factorizing numbers, it is easy to verify that a set of factors multiplied result in the input number, but it is not easy to check that all factors are indeed prime numbers.</para>
<para>In all cases, it is useful to know that the hostnames of the clients that have generated computation results are annotated in the output of the dispense and host tools. If you encounter an incorrect result, you can easily determine which client was responsible for it and which other results were sent to this client (and are therefore unreliable). This is very useful to resolve the problems without having to restart the whole computation afterwards; instead, you only need to recompute the results that were generated by the malfunctioning clients.</para>
</section>

</section>

<section><title>History</title>
<para>The Dispense2 toolbox is loosely based on the "Dispense Package" by Stephen Montgomery-Smith, which is available from:
<ulink url="http://www.math.missouri.edu/~stephen/software/dispense/">http://www.math.missouri.edu/~stephen/software/dispense/</ulink>.</para>

<para>The reason for rewriting the tools in Python, was the lack of portability of the Dispense Package to other operating systems than FreeBSD (most notably Windows). Since the whole point of distributed computing is the use of different systems to work on a common task, portability is a major feature of the Dispense2 tools. The more platforms are supported, the more computers can potentially participate in a computation project.</para></section>

<section><title>License</title>
<para>Dispense2 is distributed under the terms of the GNU General Public License,
version 2 or higher. Get a copy at: <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html">http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html</ulink>.</para>
</section>

</article>
